Marc Girons Lopez

Address Oberwiesenstrasse 50

Birth

8050 Zurich (Switzerland)

5 September 1986

Barcelona (Spain)

Website Telephone

E-mail

gironslopez.me +41 (0) 78-775 89 93 gironslopez@gmail.com

Citizenship Spain

I am a hydrologist with an interdisciplinary background working as postdoctoral researcher at the University of Zurich. I aim at contributing to build up knowledge and understanding about water related issues to make society more resilient and sustainable. I believe in continuous learning and communication and I am also interested in societal behaviour and data analysis. Everything is connected!

Professional Experience

feb 2017 — aug 2018 Postdoctoral Researcher · University of Zurich (Switzerland)

My research focuses on improving the realism of the snow routine of the HBV rainfall-runoff model while maintaining a low model uncertainty. Also, I contributed to glacio-hydrological modelling of future peak flows in remote

valleys of Tajikistan.

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Graduate Teaching Assistant • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Lecturing, leading seminars, and leading and assisting in laboratory and field

activities for both undergraduate and graduate courses.

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Graduate Research Assistant • Uppsala University (Sweden)

Design and implementation of research projects within hydrology and natural disaster science, including defining research questions, modelling, data

analysis, and reporting scientific results.

jun 2009 — aug 2009 — Quality Control Intern • Laboratori Català de Control (Spain)

Quality control tests of cement, concrete and anchorages. Tests of soil properties, water sampling and analysis. Defining procedures for adopting ISO

rules.

jul 2008 — sep 2008 Environmental Consultant Intern • URS Corporation (Spain)

Environmental control tests of petrol stations, soil decontamination, and hydrogeological data processing. Fauna and sediment sampling for water

quality control of rivers and dams.

Education

aug 2011 — oct 2016 Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) · Uppsala University (Sweden)

Hydrology and Water Resources Science

Thesis: Information Needs for Water Resource and Risk Management:

Hydro-Meteorological Data Value and Non-Traditional Information.

aug 2009 — jun 2011 Master of Science (MSc) · Uppsala University (Sweden)

Earth Sciences (Hydrology/Hydrogeology)

Thesis: Modelling Climatic and Hydrological Variability in Lake Babati, North-

ern Tanzania.

sep 2004 — jun 2009 Bachelor of Science (BSc) · Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (Spain)

Geology

aug 2007 – jun 2008 Exchange student • Université Joseph Fourier – Grenoble I (France)

Geology and Earth Sciences

Publications

Peer-reviewed Publications

- Di Baldassarre, G., Nohrstedt, D., Mård, J., Burchardt, S., Albin, C., Bondesson, S., Breinl, K., Deegan, F. M., Fuentes, D., **Girons Lopez, M.**, Granberg, M., Nyberg, L., Rydstedt Nyman, M., Rhodes, E., Troll, V., Young, S., Walch, C., and Parker, C. F. (2018). "An Integrative Research Framework to Unravel the Interplay of Natural Hazards and Vulnerabilities". In: *Earth's Future*. ISSN: 2328-4277. DOI: 10.1002/2017EF000764.
- Breinl, K., Di Baldassarre, G., **Girons Lopez, M.**, Hagenlocher, M., Vico, G., and Rutgersson, A. (2017). "Can weather generation capture precipitation patterns across climates, spatial scales and under data scarcity?" In: *Scientific Reports* 7.5449. ISSN: 2045-2322. DOI: 10.1038/s41598-017-05822-y.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Di Baldassarre, G., and Seibert, J. (2017). "Impact of social preparedness on flood early warning systems". In: *Water Resources Research* 53.1, pp. 522-534. ISSN: 1944-7973. DOI: 10.1002/2016WR019387.
- **Girons Lopez, M.** and Seibert, J. (2016). "Influence of hydro-meteorological data spatial aggregation on streamflow modelling". In: *Journal of Hydrology* 541, pp. 1212–1220. ISSN: 0022-1694. DOI: 10.1016/j.jhydrol.2016.08.026.
- Mbanguka, R. P., Lyon, S. W., Holmgren, K., **Girons Lopez, M.**, and Jarsjö, J. (2016). "Water Balance and Level Change of Lake Babati, Tanzania: Sensitivity to Hydroclimatic Forcings". In: *Water* 8.12. ISSN: 2073-4441. DOI: 10.3390/w8120572.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Wennerström, H., Nordén, L.-Å., and Seibert, J. (2015). "Location and Density of Rain Gauges for the Estimation of Spatial Varying Precipitation". In: *Geografiska Annaler: Series A, Physical Geography* 97.1, pp. 167–179. ISSN: 1468-0459. DOI: 10.1111/geoa.12094.

Publications in Preparation

- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Vis, M., and Seibert, J. (2018a). "Assessing the Use of Additional Data for Temperature-Index Snowmelt Modelling in Hydrological Models".
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Vis, M., and Seibert, J. (2018b). "Evaluating the Complexity of Snow Processes for Distribution Function Hydrological Models".
- Rivera, S. J., **Girons Lopez, M.**, Seibert, J., and Minsker, B. S. (2018a). "Flood depth determination using volunteered geographical information".
- Rivera, S. J., **Girons Lopez, M.**, Seibert, J., and Minsker, B. S. (2018b). "Probabilistic Flood Mapping Using Volunteered Geographical Information".

Theses

- **Girons Lopez, M.** (Oct. 2016). "Information Needs for Water Resource and Risk Management: Hydro-Meteorological Data Value and Non-Traditional Information". PhD thesis. Uppsala University, Department of Earth Sciences, p. 74. ISBN: 978-91-554-9679-1.
- **Girons Lopez, M.** (2011). "Modelling Climatic and Hydrological Variability in Lake Babati, Northern Tanzania". MA thesis. Stockholm University, Department of Physical Geography, p. 57.

Conference Contributions

- Fourniadis, Y., Free, M., Manning, J., Beckett, O., Bolch, T., and **Girons Lopez, M.** (Feb. 2018). "Impact Of Climate Change On Glaciers And Glacial Runoff In Tajikistan". In: *New Dimensions for Natural Hazards in Asia: An AOGS-EGU Joint Conference* (Tagaytay, Philippines).
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Vis, M., and Seibert, J. (Feb. 2018a). "Realism versus simplicity in the snow routine of the HBV model". In: *SnowHydro 2018* (Heidelberg, Germany).
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Vis, M., and Seibert, J. (Apr. 2018b). "Realism vs Simplicity: Depicting snow processes in a simple hydrological model". In: *Geophysical Research Abstracts* (Vienna, Austria). Vol. 20. EGU, p. 1266.
- Breinl, K., Di Baldassarre, G., and **Girons Lopez, M.** (Apr. 2017). "Reduced-complexity multi-site rainfall generation: one million years over night using the model TripleM". In: *Geophysical Research Abstracts* (Vienna, Austria). Vol. 19. EGU, p. 3065.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Di Baldassarre, G., and Seibert, J. (Apr. 2017). "Strengthening flood warning systems: the benefits of encouraging social preparedness". In: *Geophysical Research Abstracts* (Vienna, Austria). Vol. 19. EGU, p. 14212.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Vis, M., and Seibert, J. (Oct. 2017a). "Re-thinking the snow routine of HBV". In: *Cool models for a warm climate operational snow models for the present and future climate* (Finse, Norway).
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Vis, M., and Seibert, J. (Apr. 2017b). "Realism versus simplicity in the snow routine of the HBV model". In: *Geophysical Research Abstracts* (Vienna, Austria). Vol. 19. EGU, p. 13395.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Di Baldassarre, G., Grabs, T., Halldin, S., and Seibert, J. (Apr. 2016). "Exploring the Role of Social Memory of Floods for Designing Flood Early Warning Operations". In: *Geophysical Research Abstracts* (Vienna, Austria). Vol. 18. EGU, p. 15179.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Di Baldassarre, G., and Seibert, J. (June 2016). "Impact of Social Memory on the Efficiency of Flood Early Warning Systems (FEWS)". In: *INTERPRAEVENT 2016 Extended Abstracts* (Lucerne, Switzerland). International Research Society INTERPRAEVENT, p. 220. ISBN: 978-3-901164-23-1.
- Rivera, S. J., **Girons Lopez, M.**, Seibert, J., and Minsker, B. S. (Dec. 2016). "Probabilistic Flood Mapping using Volunteered Geographical Information". In: *2016 Fall Meeting, AGU* (San Francisco, California). AGU, p. 134525.
- Rivera, S. J., **Girons Lopez, M.**, Minsker, B. S., and Seibert, J. (July 2015). "Probabilistic Flood Mapping using Volunteered Geographical Information". In: *3rd CUAHSI Conference on Hydroinformatics* (Tuscaloosa, Alabama). CUAHSI.
- **Girons Lopez, M.**, Seibert, J., Halldin, S., and Wennerström, H. (July 2013). "Value of distributed precipitation for flood early warning: A case study for a pre-alpine catchment in Switzerland". In: *Knowledge for the Future Joint IAHS-IAPSO-IASPEI Assembly* (Gothenburg, Sweden).
- Mbanguka, R. P., **Girons Lopez, M.**, and Jarsjö, J. (Apr. 2013). "A Water Balance Model for assessing Hydro Climatic Variability in Tropical Lake Systems: Application to Lake Babati and Lake Emakat, Nothern Tanzania". In: *Geophysical Research Abstracts* (Vienna, Austria). Vol. 15. EGU, p. 3154.

Teaching

Teaching experience

2011	Global Hydrology 10 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Field activities (10 hours).
2011 — 2012	Distribution and Treatment of Drinking Water 5 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Laboratory activities, grading (20 hours).
2012	Statistical Methods in Hydrology 5 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Grading (5 hours).
2012 — 2014	Groundwater and Runoff modelling 15 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Laboratory activities, grading (20 hours).
2012 — 2014	Runoff 5 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Laboratory activities (10 hours).
2012 — 2015	Soil Mechanics and Engineering Geology 10 ECTS; first cycle (Uppsala University) Lecturing and grading (10 hours).
2012 — 2016	Hydrology and Water Resource Management 10 ECTS; first cycle (Uppsala University) Lecturing, field and laboratory activities, grading (70 hours).
2012 — 2016	GIS for Water Resources 5 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Laboratory activities, grading (60 hours).
2013	Climate and Landscape 10 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Lecturing (10 hours).
2013 — 2014	Field Course in Earth Science II 5 ECTS; first cycle (Uppsala University) Field activities (20 hours).
2013 — 2016	Meteorology, hydrology and Environmental Measurement Techniques 15 ECTS; first cycle (Uppsala University) Field and laboratory activities, and seminars (70 hours).
2015 — 2016	Field Methods in Earth Science 5 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Field and laboratory activities (60 hours).
2015 — 2016	Groundwater and Surface Water Modelling 10 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Lecturing, laboratory activities and seminars (20 hours).
2015	Snow Physics and Hydrology 10 ECTS; second cycle (Uppsala University) Laboratory activities (10 hours).

University pedagogical education

2015 Academic Teacher Training Course

5 Weeks, full-time (Uppsala University)

Representation Duties

2014 — 2016 PhD student representative • CNDS

I was elected as PhD student representative to the Program Board of the

Centre for Natural Disaster Science (CNDS).

2013 PhD student representative • Uppsala University

I was elected as PhD student representative to the Board of the Department

of Earth Sciences at Uppsala University.

2007 Student representative • Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona

I was elected as student representative to the Board of the Section of Geol-

ogy at Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona.

Skills

Programming Python • Matlab • LATEX• Fortran

 $\textbf{Software} \hspace{1cm} \textbf{ArcGIS} \cdot \textbf{QGIS} \cdot \textbf{HBV} \cdot \textbf{Git} \cdot \textbf{Inkscape} \cdot \textbf{Linux}$

InstrumentationCampbell data loggers • hydro-meteorological sensorsLanguagesNativeCatalan • Spanish

Full professional proficiency English

Professional working proficiency Swedish • French

Elementary proficiency German

Other Swedish driving license (B)

Grants, Awards, & Honours

2017 Travel grant · Association Suisse de Géographie

I obtained a travel grant to participate in the first Finse International Snow

Workshop in Finse (Norway) and present the results of my research.

2016 Photo contest winner • EGU

Winner of the 2016 European Geosciences Union Photo contest with the

photograph "Living Flows".

2015 Research Fellowship • CUAHSI

I was sponsored by the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrological Sciences (CUAHSI) to participate in the first National Flood Interoperability Experiment (NFIE) at the US National Water Center in

Tuscaloosa (Alabama).

2014 Travel grant • Liljewalchs Foundation

I obtained a travel grant to participate in the EGU 2016 General Assembly in

Vienna (Austria) and present the results of my research.

2009 Scholarship • Swedish-Spanish Foundation

I obtained a scholarship from the Swedish-Spanish Foundation for the Promotion of Education and Studies to help cover the expenses as a Master

student in Uppsala University.

2007 Scholarship • Erasmus Programme

I obtained a scholarship to help cover the expenses of spending a year at the Université Joseph Fourier in Grenoble (France) as exchange student.

Other Activities

2016 - Translator • Planet Press

I translate short scientific articles for kids from the European Geosciences

Union (EGU) Planet Press initiative from English to Spanish.

2013 **Volunteer • IAHS**

I volunteered supporting the organisation of the 2013 IAHS, IAPSO, IAPSEI

Joint Assembly in Gothenburg (Sweden).